Preliminary Inventory to the Horia Georgescu Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Horia Georgescu Papers
1921-1991
87018
Hoover Institution Archives
16 manuscript boxes (6.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to Romanian diplomacy during World War II, and to postwar Romanian emigre affairs. Includes a few papers of the Romanian diplomat Catalin Vladescu-Olt.
Georgescu, Horia, 1914-1988
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical note
Romanian vice-consul, Jerusalem (1940–41), second secretary of legation, Rome (1943–44), first secretary of legation, Paris (1946–47).
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1987.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Diplomats--Romania.; France--Foreign relations--Romania.; France.; Italy--Foreign relations--Romania.; Italy.; Middle East.; Romania--Foreign relations--France.; Romania--Foreign relations--Italy.; Romania.; Romanians in foreign countries.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Romania.; World War, 1939-1945.
- ROYAL MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS: (Box 1-2)
  - Laws and decrees governing the organization of the Royal Ministry of Foreign Affairs from, 1921 to 1946.
  - Romanian State Protocol: decree of, August,1944.
- LISTS of the Diplomatic, Consular and Clerical Personnel of the Royal Romanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs: including issues of the MONITORUL OFICIAL (the official gazette)., 1938-1947
- POLITICAL DOCUMENTS:, 26 June, 1940 - 27 December, 1945.
- The RECOGNITION OF THE ROMANIAN GOVERNMENT by Britain and the USA.
- LISTS of the states (a) at war with Romania; (b) with which diplomatic relations were broken by one or either side, (February, 1946).
- DIPLOMATIC REPORTS:
  - ROMANIAN LEGATION IN ITALY (Venice, by Horia Georgescu), 1944
  - ROMANIAN CONSULATE GENERAL IN PALESTINE: report on H.G. and the situation in Palestine in by Virgil Zaborovschi., 1940-41
- ROMANIAN LEGATION IN PARIS:
  - political reports, 1945-46
  - report about the French Press, 1945-46
  - various Diplomatic Lists in Paris
- ROMANIAN LEGATION IN LONDON: Reports by the Press Service on the state of the British Press, 1945 and 1946.
- Letters, documents, photographs and mementos concerning Gr. Gr. Constantinesco to be added to his papers already in the possession of the Hoover Institution (including a manuscript by Charles-Adolphe Cantac zene, a former Romanian diplomat).
  General note
  Constantinesco Coll.
- ROMANIAN FOREIGN AND ECONOMIC POLICY TOWARDS GERMANY as reflected in the reports of the ECONOMIC SERVICE (Directiunea Economica) of the Romanian Foreign Ministry, under Ion Christu: a continuous effort to stop or diminish increasing German demands upon Romania's economy during the war., (1938-1942)
  (Left by Catalin Vladescu-Olt (1912-1986) Romanian diplomat, with mementos of his first wife, Beatrice, nee Schmidlin, assistant to N. Titulescu and Ion Christu, and their photo-portraits).
- SPECIAL FILE: Some activities of Romanian Democratic Exiles in Great Britain, mainly within the framework of THE BRITISH ROMANIAN ASSOCIATION (A.C.A.R.D.A.) of which HORIA GEORGESCU was Secretary General, 1965-1985.
- EXILE I: "SHADOWS AND SORROWS" (Legionarii, G.A. Pordea, Ion Ratiu - "Cu scârbà si mànie"; V.V. Tilea.) (Box 3)
- EXILE II: "SHADOWS AND SORROWS" (Agenti, "Biserica Rosie"; Foreign dupes, junketeers, etc., Plastografi.) (Box 3-4)
- EXILE III: UNSUCCESSFUL ATTEMPTS AT A REAL UNION OF ROMANIAN EXILES. (Box 4)
- EXILE IV: "ACHIEVEMENTS AND DISAPPOINTMENTS" (ACARDA = British Romanian Association), 1965-1985. (+ 1985-1987.) (Box 5)
- DOCUMENTS I: Consiliu National Romàn; Al. Cretzianu, Constantin Visoianu. Regele Mihai (1) + (2). Mircea Ionnitiu:, "23 August 1944". (Box 5-6)
- DOCUMENTS II: LEONARD KIRSCHEN FILE: Manuscript: political situation in Romania, trials, prisons, etc. Plus Varia Re: Iuliu Maniu; Ion Antonescu; N. Titulescu (Raymond Lacoste, Gh. Anastasiu), C.M. Laptew re Titulescu, letter re "boieri româani" G.V. Bumbesti: "Acest secol ar fi avut 50 de ani" H.G., etc.), (1950 (Box 6)
- ROMANIAN MATTERS I: (Box 7)
  - Transylvania - Basic and Current.
  - Bessarabia - Basic and Current.
- ROMANIAN MATTERS II: Transylvania.
- ROMANIAN MATTERS III: Transylvania - Documents. (Box 8)
- ROMANIAN MATTERS IV: Bessarabia; Aromâni; International Pen Club.
- ROMANIA BASIC: Jews in Romania; Hungary (and Transylvania). (Box 9)
- ION CARAION Correspondence of H.G. with the poet, collection of articles by H.G. and others. CAIETE CARAION published by DIALOG, etc., (1923 - 1986)
- The Foreign Office - Romania Father Gh. Calciu-Dumitreasa Nicolae Ceausescu - personal file; KESTON COLLEGE: correspondence with; Correspondence with Walter Kendall (socialist militant) and Professor Glanville Price (Aberystwyth University)., 1965 - 79; 1983 - 1986 (Box 10)
- S.L.O.M.R. (Free Trade Union in Communist Romania; RELIGIOUS PERSECUTION IN ROMANIA, (2 files). (Box 11)
- HUMAN RIGHTS: C.S.C.E., Amnesty International, Helsinki Accords concerning Romania, Documents.
- HORIA GEORGESCU: BASIC COLLECTION (Box 12)
  - Some activities of ACARDA, 1965-1985.
  - Activities in the press, etc., 1985-1988.
  - Articles and Memoirs by H.G. (to be completed)
  - Notices and Tributes following the death of H.G.
  - SPECIAL SELECTED ARTICLES, MEMOS & SOUVENIRS.
- HORIA GEORGESCU: Personal
  - 30 Years with Agence France Presse (London), 1949-1979.
  - Getting H.G.'s mother out of Romania and Power of Attorney to sell her house.
- HORIA GEORGESCU: Personal Papers Re (Box 13)
  - The Royal Romanian Foreign Ministry.
  - The Royal Romanian Legation - Rome.
  - The Royal Romanian Legation - Paris. Plus Medal, Passports, Seals, etc.